<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
   <header>
      <title>Documenting the South Sámi lexicon file</title>
      <authors>
         <person email="trond.trosterud@hum.uit.no" name="Trond Trosterud"/>
      </authors>
   </header>
   <body>
      <section>
         <title>Documenting the South Sámi lexicon file</title>
         <section>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The sma lexicon is organised the same way as the North Sámi lexicon, cf. <a
            href="../sme/docu-sme-flowchart.html">the flowchart of North Sámi</a>.</p>
         </section>
         <section>
            <title>The nouns</title>
            <p>The noun stems are stored in <code>gt/sma/noun-sma-lex.txt</code>, whereas the morphology is found in
            <code>gt/sma/sma-lex.txt</code>. It was made by converting the original Moshagen / Trosterud sma lexicon to
            the Xerox format. The lexical rules are taken from Karttunen's alternative formulation of our file. His
            original is found in the archive of original files (Contact Trond for reference, if needed).</p>
            <p>The nouns are divided into three stem classes, the N_IE nouns (gåetie, etc.), the N_OE nouns (bearkoe,
            etc) and the N_OTHER nouns (all other ones, bi- and trisyllabic alike).</p>
            <p>The case forms fall in three different groups: Forms unique to each of the three stem classes (listed
            under each sublexicon), forms with -j- in the N_OE class and -i- in the other ones (with separate i- and j-
            sublexica and a common suffix lexicon), and forms common to all stem classes (covered in a common
            continuation lexicon).</p>
            <p>Here is a list of the lexica (to be documented)</p>
            <source>
 N_ODD
 N_ODD_NODISIMP
 ÅABPETJH        !default N_ODD plural lexicon
 N_ODD_C         !these words have consonant-ending in nominative
 AAJEGE          !Sg+Nom=Aajege/Aajeh  Sg+Cmp=Aajeh-
 AAREGE          !Sg+Nom=Aarege/Aareh  Sg+Cmp=Aarege-/Aareh-
 BAARTEGE        !Sg+Nom=baartege/baarth  Sg+Cmp=baartege-/baarth-
 GAAJSEGE        !Sg+Nom=gaajsege/gaajsh  Sg+Cmp=gaajsh-
 LAADTEGE        !Sg+Nom=laadtege  Sg+Cmp=laadth-
 SAADTEGE        !Sg+Nom=saadtege  Sg+Cmp=saadtege-/saadth-
 LEEJJEGE        !Sg+Nom=leejjege  Sg+Cmp=leejjeh-
 DEAKEHKE        !Sg+Nom=deakehke/deakah  Sg+Cmp=deakehke-/deakah-
 ÅERUVE
 BÅERUVE
 VUANOVE
 BÅERUJE
 IJE_ODD
 DAKTERE
 N_IE
 VUELIE
 TJIDTJIE
 TJÅENIEH       !ie plural lexicon
 N_OE_UML
 N_OE
 LAAHKOE
 GAAROEH        !-oe plural
 MAANA
 AAHKA
 NIEJTE
 MAAKE
 JOVKEMES 
        
        </source>
         </section>
         <section>
            <title>The proper nouns</title>
            <p>tbw.</p>
         </section>
         <section>
            <title>The adjectives</title>
            <p>The continuation lexica are built on the following convention:</p>
            <p><code>attrsuffix_PREDSUFFIX_STEMTYPECOMPTYPE</code></p>
            <p>A letter C in the beginning of the suffix marks consonant. There may be more than one
            suffix both for attr and PRED, thereby the difference small/capital letters. Example:</p>
            <p><code>faelskies+CmpN/SgN+CmpN/SgG+CmpN/PlG:faelsk ies_IES_IE_EVEN</code></p>
<p>This is an even-syllabic adjective, with -ies attributive and -ies or -ie in predicative. Since
nothing is said about comparative forms, it has normal comparative and superlative inflection.</p>
         </section>
         <section>
            <title>The verbs</title>
            <p>The auxiliary <em>lea</em> and the negative verbs have been added. These verbs are irregular, and have
            thus been added without the use of any morphophonological processes.</p>
            <p>To be written: Documentation for verb lexica.</p>
         </section>
         <section>
            <title>The adpositions and prepositions</title>
            <p>The adpositions in Bergsland's grammar have been listed, in two groups, pure postpositions and combined
            pre/postpositions (named "adpositions"). Other adpositions ahve been added.</p>
         </section>
         <section>
            <title>The adverbs</title>
            <p>tbw</p>
         </section>
         <p>Last modified: $Date$, by $Author$</p>
      </section>
   </body>
</document>
