Background information on the South Saami project
=================================================

Work on South Saami today
-------------------------

Giellatekno and Divvun work on South Saami within several different
projects:

-   [The basic work: The South Saami morphological and syntactic
    analysers](j-sma.html)
-   [The South Saami spellchecker](http://divvun.no/)
-   [The Åarjelsaemien-daaroen digibaakoeh]()
-   [The South Saami OAHPA pedagogical program]()

The initial South Saami project (1998-1999)
-------------------------------------------

South Saami was the first Saami language to receive an analysis within
the Saami language technology project. Sjur Moshagen and Trond Trosterud
made a morphological parser for South Saami already in 1998, before the
Giellatekno was initiated. The parser included a morphological analysis
of the case and number inflection of nouns, without derivation and
compounding.

The original Moshagen and Trosterud files are found at Lingsoft (in the
sms directory there). They wrote an article on that parser, cf. the link
below. Later, they received some comments from Lauri Karttunen that they
(at some point) will incorporate in the article. The present sms parser
is based upon Karttunen's critique. Contrary to the original version, it
is able to generate forms as well as analysing them. As part of the
evaluation of Karttunen's comments, the southern Saami lexicon has been
transformed from Lingsoft format to Xerox format.

Later, the parser was enlarged to include handling of the closed parts
of speech. We also did some attempts to include verbal inflection, but
we did not succeed in analysing the South Saami verbs within the same
framework as for the nouns.

The article [A Two-level Parser for South
Saami](http://giellatekno.uit.no/sms-article.htm), is the most complete
documentation of the first phase of the South Saami parser.

The South Saami spell checker project (2008-2010)
-------------------------------------------------

The main focus of the Divvun 2 project was the construction and release
of a South Saami spellchecker. The spellchecker was released in december
2010.

Phase 2: The South Saami spell checker project
----------------------------------------------

The main focus of the Divvun 2 project was the construction and release
of a South Saami spellchecker. The spellchecker was released in december
2010.
